So now let's understand this problem. See, it's the same
patient, the same person, the same policy. If you
go through the cashless route, you will have to pay ₹1
extra. And today
I will tell you
why even after buying the most expensive insurance policy,
when you go for cataract surgery, you have to pay the
bill from your pocket. The
reason for this is the cashless process. The term cashless sounds
very good but actually it
is a bit deceptive because the cashless
process is not actually cashless. In that, you have to pay the
venture mount. The
biggest reason for this is the lack of knowledge of the
patients because they do not know anything about their rights and
their limits of the policies. That is why
generally they fall into this
trap. In the cashless process,
you are given a facility in
which you do
not have to use your brain at all. It is a very smooth ride.
You do not have to know what is happening. You have to
go to the hospital directly and
give them your insurance card
and you get a normal  They will give you the monofocal lens
and you will easily go cashless.
But the problem is that
many times in 90% of the cases, we see
that your actual policy limit is much
higher, let's say from Rs.
50,000 to Rs. 100,000. I have generally seen that
you have a limit of Rs. 45,000 to Rs. 50,000, but
you get only an approximate of Rs. 30,000. So, it is
very
important to verify this thing first. So, first of all, write an email to your
agent who has got your health insurance
policy or your HR
or call them and contact them and
ask them what is your limit
for cataract surgery. 99% chances are
that your limit will be
around Rs. 45,000 to Rs. 50,000. And if you go
to the hospital for cashless surgery, the
hospital will tell you that your
approved amount for cataract surgery will generally be Rs.
30,000 to Rs. 34,000.
You will have to pay the difference amount,
especially if you want to get any premium lens,
any imported lens,
toric or trifocal or edge of
lens, then the hospital will
charge you. Now what is the solution to this problem?
Such discrepancy is
because whenever the insurance company gives you a
cashless facility,
they are deducting such a high premium amount from you for providing that facility. So what should
you do?
First of all, ask your agent or
HR as to
how much amount is required in the reimbursement process in your insurance, whether there is
any capping on the cost of resorption or cataract surgery, thirdly, whether your two-
year waiting period is over or
not and lastly, is there any pre-existing
disease or any such clause due to which
your reimbursement process will stop.
Believe me, if you ask them,
they will tell you
not to get reimbursement done, you should only go for cashless treatment
and many times we see that patients are being treated
differently.  In different hospitals also, you are directed
that you should
go to that XYZ hospital and get your surgery done
there, your complete cashless process will be done there. The
catch here is that at the time when
they might be pitching you for cashless
or redirecting you to
some other hospital or some other surgeon,
you will not be told at that time.
After the surgery, when the final bill and
discharge is sent, then the
biggest problem arises at that time because your
approved amount will be a little less and you are
stuck in the hospital, then you will have to pay
the amount. This is a very common practice.
We face this thing almost on a daily basis.
So now what is the way to avoid this?
When you have discussed all the
four points with your HR or your policy
agent, then you tell them that I
only want SI reimbursement, I do
not want cashless. After that, you should leave cashless and
start the process for reimbursement and all your bills, your
discharge, all your even OPD and
IPD bills, a breakup bill.  Implant
's tax invoice, your test reports,
your prescription,
your scans, collect all these
and fill it in your claim form and submit
it along with the cancelled cheque for your reimbursement
and
before getting the reimbursement processed, always keep your
agent and your HR in the loop via email
so that there is no confusion later,
first confirm with them
how much amount will be rebated, after that submit it
for reimbursement,
I will keep giving you similar tips and tricks,
if you liked the video then like and
share, subscribe, if you want to
connect with our team you can consult by calling on the IVR number,
thank you